<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>syslog</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/</link><description>Recent content on syslog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 01:22:00 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Shadowrun Anarchy: Simplified or Simplistic Rules?</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2022-07-29-shadowrun-anarchy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 01:22:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2022-07-29-shadowrun-anarchy/</guid><description>Thanks to SUSD&amp;rsquo;s video on Android: Netrunner, I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself playing quite some matches of the card game recently. The fact that the cyberpunk theme being is well represented in the mechanics has captivated me very dearly &amp;mdash; so much so that it got me wanting to tell a story in a similar world. That&amp;rsquo;s when I started going through my old stuff looking for a Shadowrun Tabletop RPG book.</description></item><item><title>Umineko and the Mystery Genre (spoiler-free)</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2022-04-10-umineko/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 20:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2022-04-10-umineko/</guid><description>During the last 4 months I&amp;rsquo;ve used a total of 160 hours of my free time to &amp;ldquo;play&amp;rdquo; (read would be more fitting) Umineko no Naku Koro ni, a Japanese visual novel split into 8 parts originally released between 2007 and 2010. Translated as &amp;ldquo;Umineko When They Cry&amp;rdquo;, the story is about how, during the 2 days of the yearly Ushiromiya family conference, the people present are killed in apparently impossible murders, with the bodies of the victims found in rooms locked from the inside.</description></item><item><title>Movie Review: Drunken Master (1978)</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 14:25:23 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/</guid><description>Drunken Master is one of the movies that helped set-up Jackie Chan&amp;rsquo;s career as a martial artist, along with Snake in the Eagle&amp;rsquo;s Shadow and The Young Master. It has almost all the elements that became synonymous with Chan&amp;rsquo;s later movies: Great fighting mixed with comedy and his high energy charisma. The only thing that&amp;rsquo;s missing is the crazy stunts, but the movie has enough kung-fu to make up for it.</description></item><item><title>Movie Review: Cliff Walkers (2021)</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 13:52:46 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/</guid><description>Cliff Walkers follows 4 Chinese spies trying to reach the Japanese-dominated city of Harbin, where they should await for further instructions. However, the fascists are aware of their plans, and send their agents to infiltrate and sabotage the mission.
This film has spies doing what they do best: handling information. The first scene has the protagonists split into 2 groups, with no radios or other ways to contact each other. In a following scene, when one of the groups learns that they&amp;rsquo;re being watched, they must pass this information to their teammates without busting their identity.</description></item><item><title>Huion HS64 Drivers</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2020-08-25-hs64-tablet-drivers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2020-08-25-hs64-tablet-drivers/</guid><description>Due to the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic, I found myself with too much free time; so much that I decided to try a new hobby: Drawing. I don&amp;rsquo;t plan to take it seriously, I just wanted to scribble something while I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything better to do.
So I decided to borrow a pen-tablet from a friend who has a Wacom. It was a pretty neat device. Simply plug it in and everything worked out of the box.</description></item></channel></rss>