<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Movie on syslog</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/tags/movie/</link><description>Recent content in Movie on syslog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 14:25:23 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/tags/movie/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Movie Review: Drunken Master (1978)</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 14:25:23 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/</guid><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/feature.jpg" width="600" height="337"><p><strong><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/11230-jui-kuen"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >Drunken Master</a></strong> is one of the movies that helped set-up Jackie Chan&rsquo;s career as a martial artist, along with <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/11537-se-ying-diu-sau"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >Snake in the Eagle&rsquo;s Shadow</a></em> and <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/11563"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >The Young Master</a></em>. It has almost all the elements that became synonymous with Chan&rsquo;s later movies: Great fighting mixed with comedy and his high energy charisma. The only thing that&rsquo;s missing is the crazy stunts, but the movie has enough kung-fu to make up for it. In fact, this is one of the main differences when you compare this film with other of Chan&rsquo;s works: Here, <strong>everybody <em>fights</em></strong>. And they don&rsquo;t just throw some punches around; this is a martial arts movie, after all.</p>













    
    

    
    
        
    

    <div class="w-100 center my-2">
        <figure class="w-100 m-auto maxw-600px">
            
                <video muted autoplay loop tabindex="0" aria-description="Fight scene featuring Jackie Chan and Linda Lin. She owns him using only kicks." src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/videos/jackie-chan-vs-linda-lin.mp4" class="w-100 floating"></video>
            
            
            
            <figcaption aria-hidden="true" class="caption">Jackie Chan fighting Linda Lin.</figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<p>In a Jackie Chan movie, what usually happens in fight scenes is: Jackie starts unarmed against a pack of grunts, and slowly takes them out, maybe breaking some bones in the process. It&rsquo;s not like the grunts don&rsquo;t know how to fight, but all they do are simple moves. A punch here, a kick there; maybe do some jumps. <strong>The only one doing the complex stuff is Chan</strong>. And when there is a one-on-one fight, Jackie usually has a disadvantage: This makes for scenes where no matter the number of enemies or their strength, Chan has to climb from the bottom-up to win, leading to amazing stunts and moves in order to achieve the feat.</p>
<p>In this film, all the fights (with only one exception, I think) are one-on-one. They have a much more explicit rhythm and the actors do their moves in sync, connecting one strike to the next. It&rsquo;s more akin to watching a (very cool) ballet session, in a way that got me thinking about <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/tv/890-neon-genesis-evangelion/season/1/episode/9"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >that</a></em> Evangelion episode. Both fighters are working together to make the action flow, which is a different experience when compared to &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; Jackie Chan fighting scenes.</p>
<p>Since <strong>everybody is doing complex moves</strong> (instead of just Jackie doing them), the pace is more steady (but not calm), as opposed to the more erratic flow commonly seen in modern action movies: <em>Punch, wait. Kick, wait. Pull, wait.</em> Of course, this has its reason to be: the moves are hard to do, plus you don&rsquo;t want to hurt anyone involved. But it ends up pulling the fighting closer to the aforementioned <em>ballet session</em>, and away from the more desirable <em>crazy stunt scene</em>.</p>













    
    
        
            
            

            
        
    

    
    
        
    

    <div class="w-100 center my-2">
        <figure class="w-100 m-auto maxw-600px">
            
            
                <a href="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/images/eva-dancing.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                <img src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/images/eva-dancing_hu3c1b0c430d98e6c79974eccd97e71882_208255_600x460_fit_q75_h2_box.webp" loading="lazy" width="600" height="373" title="The Eva pilots must fight in sync to defeat a cloning enemy in episode 9." alt="The Eva pilots must fight in sync to defeat a cloning enemy in episode 9." aria-description="A pair of mechas fighting side by side, against a pair of aliens." class="floating">
                </a>
            
            
            <figcaption aria-hidden="true" class="caption">The Eva pilots must fight in sync to defeat a cloning enemy in episode 9.</figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<p>Since we&rsquo;re talking about dancing so much, how can we not speak of the music in this film? The main theme is awesome. It feels very powerful, starting with a low, long sequence that then spikes into a very (and I mean <em>very</em>) loud section that goes speeding up until it ends. It&rsquo;s based on a Chinese folk song, the same one that inspired the main theme of <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/10617-wong-fei-hung"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >Once Upon A Time In China</a></em> 13 years later, which features the same main character, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wong_Fei-hung"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >Wong Fei Hung</a>. The structure really fits with the whole &ldquo;drunken fists&rdquo; fighting style: The slow, deep start tricks the enemy into thinking you can&rsquo;t react fast enough because of the alcohol, but then&ndash; <strong>BAM</strong>! You hit them in the face.</p>













    
    

    
    
        
    

    <div class="w-100 center my-2">
        <figure class="w-100 m-auto maxw-600px">
            
            
            
                <audio title="Music with traditional chinese instruments. Strong, rhythmic and slow drums on the background. After the one minute mark, suddenly, very high wind instruments join and the music speeds up." aria-description="Music with traditional chinese instruments. Strong, rhythmic and slow drums on the background. After the one minute mark, suddenly, very high wind instruments join and the music speeds up." class="w-100 floating" src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/audios/main-theme.aac" controls></audio>
            
            <figcaption aria-hidden="true" class="caption">The main theme. Beware of 01:04.</figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<p>The rest of the music is fine, with an honorable mention to the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FY5M3NsZ_Uk"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >track</a> that plays in the comedy scene where Jackie is punished, which sounds fun and lighthearted. And speaking of comedy, this movie has plenty of it, and it&rsquo;s very good. The movie&rsquo;s tagline on TMDB is <em>&ldquo;The Original Kung Fu Comedy!&rdquo;</em>, and it certainly feels like it. You can&rsquo;t stop smiling when Chan plays with his instructor&rsquo;s hat, or when he stops fighting just to eat. When he cheats in his training with Beggar So, or even when his own dad punishes him for his recklessness, you can&rsquo;t help but to feel like a child laughing at such simple jokes; and when they&rsquo;re perfectly paired with the action, it&rsquo;s some of the best fun you can have while watching a movie. So much so that I think <strong>the comedy here is better than in Jackie Chan&rsquo;s later works</strong>. But there are some moments where that bar goes <em>low</em>. The scene where Chan farts in someone&rsquo;s face hits hard: You &ldquo;wake up&rdquo; from all the fun you were having and ask yourself, <em>&ldquo;who thought this was funny?&rdquo;</em>. Luckily, it only happens once or twice.</p>













    
    

    
    
        
    

    <div class="w-100 center my-2">
        <figure class="w-100 m-auto maxw-600px">
            
                <video muted autoplay loop tabindex="0" aria-description="Fight scene featuring Jackie Chan and Yuen Siu-tien. It&#39;s good, but the rhythm is not very dynamic: it just goes back and forth, and back, and forth..." src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-08-07-drunken-master-1978-review/videos/jackie-chan-vs-yuen-siu-tin.mp4" class="w-100 floating"></video>
            
            
            
            <figcaption aria-hidden="true" class="caption">You can see in some moments Jackie being sort of stiff. This is one of his earlier works.</figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<p>Overall, this is a quirky and fun movie. If you don&rsquo;t mind subpar acting or goofiness, and want to have some good laughs, I would recommend this movie. If you like other Chan&rsquo;s works (or just fighting movies in general), this is a must-watch, and a masterclass in action-comedy.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Movie Review: Cliff Walkers (2021)</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 13:52:46 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/</guid><description><![CDATA[<img src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/feature.jpg" width="600" height="337"><p><strong><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/639557-impasse"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >Cliff Walkers</a></strong> follows 4 Chinese spies trying to reach the Japanese-dominated city of Harbin, where they should await for further instructions. However, the fascists are aware of their plans, and send their agents to infiltrate and sabotage the mission.</p>
<p>This film has spies doing what they do best: handling information. The first scene has the protagonists split into 2 groups, with no radios or other ways to contact each other. In a following scene, when one of the groups learns that they&rsquo;re being watched, they must pass this information to their teammates without busting their identity. In another, they must schedule a meeting without seeing each other. The challenge of transmitting/receiving information is the base for the whole movie. The Japanese suspect they have a mole, so they&rsquo;re also careful when sharing information among them. The film goes back and forth like this, alternating between scenes following the Japanese or Chinese teams. All the characters have a sharp mind, and will play tricks to withhold or extract information from others. The tension starts at the 5-minute mark and lasts throughout the session. <strong>It feels exactly how a spy movie should</strong>.</p>













    
    
        
            
            

            
        
    

    
    
        
    

    <div class="w-100 center my-2">
        <figure class="w-100 m-auto maxw-600px">
            
            
                <a href="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/images/cliff-walkers-1.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                <img src="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2021-07-28-cliff-walkers-2021-review/images/cliff-walkers-1_hu294199021d3661b22e6615e8e5872821_129270_600x460_fit_q75_h2_box.webp" loading="lazy" width="600" height="251" title="A visual representation of the movie&rsquo;s atmosphere." alt="A visual representation of the movie&rsquo;s atmosphere." aria-description="A woman with a black hat watching from a corner." class="floating">
                </a>
            
            
            <figcaption aria-hidden="true" class="caption">A visual representation of the movie&rsquo;s atmosphere.</figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<p>While the writer has said this is a movie where spies are &ldquo;portrayed as people with emotions&rdquo;, I couldn&rsquo;t connect with any of the characters. But I wouldn&rsquo;t say this is a bad thing, I actually think it&rsquo;s good. There are moments where the tension will ease and the characters will shed tears or talk about their past, but they represent a minor slice of the movie&rsquo;s length (it lasts 2 hours). They use just enough time so that you don&rsquo;t feel like you&rsquo;re watching emotionless robots. But this means that the time not being used to make the spies more human is being used to build up the tension, which represents the <strong>absolute best aspect of this film</strong>.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I can&rsquo;t say I enjoyed the movie to it&rsquo;s fullest. There were moments where <strong>I couldn&rsquo;t absorb new information fast enough</strong>. All the characters wear the same clothes, which makes it kinda hard to know who is who. This leads to scenes where you don&rsquo;t understand what just happened. A character/event flowchart would be a welcome companion while watching it.</p>
<p>From what I&rsquo;ve been able to research, this is actually a prequel to the 2012 TV show &ldquo;悬崖&rdquo; (Cliff) by the same writer, Quan Yongxian. In an <a href="https://inf.news/entertainment/bd5332246260958e06dc8ead644ec3da.html"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >interview</a>, he said that in 2015 he had written the script for this prequel as a 60-episode show. <strong>If this had been a TV show &mdash; or even a book &mdash;, where things could flow in a more friendly pace, this would&rsquo;ve been an absolute must-watch</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Overall, it&rsquo;s a very good movie, and I recommend anyone interested to watch it</strong>. Even though you&rsquo;ll scratch your head sometimes and may wish to rewind a bit to understand what is happening, the movie is perfectly enjoyable without the aforementioned flowchart.</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>