<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tech on syslog</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/tags/tech/</link><description>Recent content in Tech on syslog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/tags/tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Huion HS64 Drivers</title><link>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2020-08-25-hs64-tablet-drivers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pietrocarrara.github.io/en/posts/2020-08-25-hs64-tablet-drivers/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Due to the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic, I found myself with too much free time; so much that I decided to try a new
hobby: Drawing. I don&rsquo;t plan to take it seriously, I just wanted to scribble something while I don&rsquo;t have anything
better to do.</p>
<p>So I decided to borrow a pen-tablet from a friend who has a Wacom. It was a pretty neat device.
Simply plug it in and everything worked out of the box. I even managed to get some playtime in osu! with it.</p>
<p>I returned it after 2~3 weeks, and decided I should buy one. I did some research, and Huion devices
had lower prices; since I won&rsquo;t take drawing seriously, I chose their HS64 model.</p>
<p>When it got here, the device wasn&rsquo;t plug-n-play, but installing the <a href="https://github.com/DIGImend/digimend-kernel-drivers"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >digimend</a> drivers fixed this. At least partially.</p>
<p>Two things didn&rsquo;t work:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Wacom tools didn&rsquo;t recognize the device, so things like configuring the active area weren&rsquo;t possible (at least not in a simple way).</li>
<li>Even though I could use the pen and its buttons, the 4 buttons present on the tablet weren&rsquo;t recognized.</li>
</ul>
<p>That was when I remembered this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=juGNPLdjLH4"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >video</a>, sort of &ldquo;little tip&rdquo; on how to get started with kernel hacking through driver development. I think I have an idea!</p>
<p>Of course, the next thing I did was clone the digimend repository and try to understand it.</p>
<p>My journey wouldn&rsquo;t last so long, however.</p>
<p>The project&rsquo;s README is very useful, so much that I was able to fix all of my problems just by reading it.
There, they tell you how to configure Xorg to use the Wacom input driver; when I did, everything worked: I could use the Wacom tools and the buttons on the tablet were responding.</p>
<p>I then discovered that the real culprit was the <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/digimend-kernel-drivers-dkms-git/"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >aur package</a> I was using did not configure this. So, instead of getting my hands dirty in driver code, I settled just writing a <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/digimend-drivers-git-dkms/"
    
    
        target="_blank" rel="noopener"
    
    >new package</a>.</p>
<p>Next time, maybe I&rsquo;ll be lucky enough to get a device with a broken driver&hellip;</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>